[Music]
what's up aush crew today we're going to
break down period 6 in the APUSH
curriculum we're going from 1865 to 1898
if you want to get real super smart on
these topics click any one of these four
videos and you'll get all the real
nitty-gritty details today we're going
to try to go quick so one important
topic is post Civil War expansion in the
post- Civil War era there's a lot of
economic opportunities out in the west
these include mining farming and the
cattle industry and the government had
actually established policies such as
the Homestead Act if you went West you
can get 160 acres of land it's not
necessarily the best land but you can
get this land for relatively cheap the
Pacific Railroad Act which established
the route for the Transcontinental
Railroad so the government is
facilitating the movement of people West
in fact the government is very active in
this process because it is going to be
the government unfortunately removing
the native people forcing them onto
reservations more on that in a moment
and giving land and Grant subsidies to
the railroad companies for this
expansion to take place so it's
important you know the role of the
government in this western expansion as
the nation is expanding West there is a
growing conservationist movement in the
country they're starting to realize that
we need to preserve some of our natural
resources and there's really a battle
between government agencies and
conservationist groups versus Corporate
interest who want to make money off the
water and the air and other things and
who's really going to control these
natural resources you do have the
department of the Interior it was
established in 1849 and its job it was
responsible for the management and
conservation of federal land and other
natural resources the US Fish Commission
is established in 1871 it's created to
preserve the Fisheries of the us so we
don't overfish and run out and really a
huge person in the conservationist
movement is John Mir in 1892 he
establishes the Sierra Club and its
whole purpose was to fight for
conservation and preservation of natural
resources and we're really going to see
in Period 7 Roosevelt Theodore Roosevelt
is going to be the guy who's going to
make this happen on a federal level
unfortunately conserv ation is not going
to be something the government's
interested in when it comes to Native
Americans their policy kind of can go
into two categories during this time
period violent conflict or assimilation
policies there's a whole bunch of
battles that take place really they're
massacres the San Creek Massacre the
Colorado militia goes in attacks and
kills over a 100 native people many of
them women and children the Battle of
Little Big Horn 1876 the Sue tribe
inspired by the leadership of Sitting
Bull kills Colonel kuster and his men in
the seventh cavalary it's also known as
kuster's Last Stand however the
government's going to come in after the
battle Little Big Horn and round up the
Sue resistance there's a ghost Dance
Movement which begins amongst the Sue
Indians in the Dakota territory where
they feel like this is a kind of
cultural Revival they're going to get
rid of the white man the Buffalo are
going to return and all is going to be
well however the US government is going
to come in with the Battle of Wounded
Knee which is the last major Indian
battle in 189 where the US Army goes
into the dtas and kills over 200 native
people once again this is more of a
massacre than it is a battle
assimilation policies tribes were often
times forced onto reservations such as
the great Sue reserve and this was
supported by laws such as the Daw
severalty Act of 1887 its whole purpose
was to end tribal ownership of land they
want the government wants native tribes
to dissolve and they want to force them
onto private Farms we also see various
Native American schools opening up with
the support of the federal government
and their goal their Duty was to
assimilate native people kill the Indian
save the man was the idea in these
schools another thing happening during
this post Civil War era is
industrialization you have large scale
production tremendous technological
change all sorts of new inventions
making life easier improv communication
networks and you see business during
this time seeking to maximize the
exploitation of a growing labor force
and natural resources key to this though
is industry leaders such as Carnegie of
course the steel guy and Rockefeller oil
who are seeking to dominate their
respective Industries through a variety
of techniques you got horizontal
integration being used where you control
all competition in a particular industry
in other words you're consolidating all
your competitors to monopolize a market
vertical integration you control all
aspect of production of manufacturing
from extracting the raw materials to
selling the finished product and in
order to eliminate or reduce competition
Business Leaders sought to establish
monopolies trust and pools they also
believed and defended their wealth with
ideas such as social Darwinism meaning
the rich are rich because they're
hardworking and the poor are poor
because they're lazy or inferior and
this is this idea of survival of the
fittest in fact one of the other key
aspects of this period is
advocating for Lazare policies in other
words the government should not regulate
business it's important you know about
the regional differences so you have the
West experiencing its own economic
growth and population growth the North
and the Midwest is industrializing but
you also have the South and after
reconstruction there was an attempt at
industrializing the southern economy
some refer to it as the new South and
there is a growth in the number of
textile Industries in the South remember
the South was largely agriculture so you
have textile mills and factories coming
into Southern States however the South
remained even though you have this idea
of the new South the South remained
primarily agriculture in fact tenant
farming and sharecropping continue to be
the predominant labor system of the
Southern economy and it's really
africanamerican laborers and poor whites
but really black laborers who are doing
much of this work in the farming and
sharecropping now during this time
during this Industrial Revolution
there's a lot of good happening
industrialization and urbanization
people moving to the cities largely
because they're looking for jobs they're
bringing about economic new economic
opportunities for immigrants and workers
people are going from rural areas to
urban areas immigrants are coming from
other countries looking for these new
economic opportunities and the workforce
is expanding we also see this time
period presenting new career
opportunities um in spite of a lot of
social Prejudice for African-Americans
and women and other disadvantaged groups
now a real key point in Period 6 is this
while industrialization brought numerous
opportunities to workers and
dramatically expanded the workforce low
wages and dangerous working conditions
continued to be a problem so yes there
were jobs but life was very difficult
for workers and as a result result of
this workers are going to fight back
they're going to fight back to try to
change this reality and you're going to
see workers organize you have the
Knights of Labor you should know about
in
1869 found it Terrence powderly is one
of the key figures in this Union they
opened up the union to all workers
skilled and unskilled workers this was
unique women and African-Americans were
also allowed to join the union however
after the Hay Market Riot where labor
unions were kind of attached to radical
movements they are going to suffer a
decline in numbers the big one though is
the American Federation of Labor the AFL
founded in 1886 make sure you know about
Samuel gomers they're going to focus on
skilled workers and they're not really
interested in social reforms they focus
on bread and butter issues practical
things like wages working condition and
hours and by 1900 it was the largest
Union in the country now workers if
you're going to evaluate the labor
movement during the Gilded Age during
this industrial era they are going to
have some successes and failures workers
did form local and National unions that
did directly confront growing corporate
power and you're going to get the
beginning of a National Labor movement
and the rise of union leaders such as
Eugene Debs you're going to see him at
the Pullman Strike and Mother Jones in
the Knights of Labor however this is
going to be followed by a lot of
failures Homestead Strike in 1892
workers at Carnegie steel are defeated
during a strike Henry Frick is going to
call out the guards and the union is
going to be busted Pullman Strike in
1894 President Cleveland is going to use
the Army in a court injunction to defeat
the strike Eugene devs will be thrown in
jail and a big problem for the unions
was also division amongst themselves you
have division between skilled and
unskilled workers ethnic and racial
groups very often workers unions were
against immigrants like the Chinese in
the west so you going to have problems
organizing you're also going to have
hostility from corporations they're
going to be hiring Pinkerton guards
yellow dog contracts pledging you won't
form a union and the government is going
to be on the sidelines offering no
protection because of the Lazare
policies of the time period it's
important you know that the lives of
farmers was also changing as they had to
adapt to meize agriculture they had to
buy all this new equipment which made
them more efficient in producing crops
and a dependence on powerful railroad
companies farmers are going to have a
lot of problems as they become more
efficient at growing crops as
agriculture becomes more and more
recognize prices are going to fall
you're also going to see unfair railroad
business practices railroad companies
will often times charge small farmers
more than large Farmers the high cost of
Machinery is going to cause huge amount
of debt Tight money supply not having
access to cheap money is going to be a
concern and of course High tariff
policies amongst many republican
administrations all of these things are
going to cause Farmers to also organize
couple of key Farmers groups you should
know about the Grange movement is going
to start off organizing social and
educational activities but later on
they're going to Lobby the state
legislators in places such as Illinois
for reforms we're going to see how that
works out in a moment the farmer
Alliance will follow in the 1870s really
in Texas they're going to be split
though because in the South you're going
to have division African-American
farmers are going to have to form their
own Farmers group called the colored
Farmers Alliance and they're going to
ignore the plight and the problems of
tenant farmers and the big one you
should know about is the one that
actually forms into a political party
the populist party they're going to be
key their strength is going to be
amongst Farmers but also amongst workers
and their platform is pretty varied in
what they want and they're really
calling for political reform and a
stronger role of the government in the
economy for instance they want the
government to own the railroad companies
two they want the free and unlimited
coinage of silver to increase the money
supply so that farmers have access to
cheap money three they want to have an
income tax which the rich would pay more
for they want to have political reform
where people would have the direct
election of senators this was not the
case at this time and five they also
want reforms such as the initiative and
referendums so that you could take away
power from these powerful business
interests and these political machines
which leads us to the government and the
role of the government Mark Twain
famously called this era the Gilded Age
and what he meant was below the surface
things are not as good as they seem
there was rampant corruption and
problems in this time period politics
during the guild age was tied heavily to
Big Business and remember there's a Laz
Fair philosophy which prevented the
government from actively regulating the
economy but it's important you
understand that you're going to see the
start of government regulation during
this period during the gra movement they
got laws pass Granger laws which
protected Farmers against abuse of the
railroad industry in the case mun versus
Illinois the Court ruled that states
could in fact regulate the railroads
however that's overturned in the Wabash
case in 1886 where the court rules the
states cannot regulate interstate
commerce trade between different states
and that's going to eventually lead to
the passage of the Interstate Commerce
Act which is going to regulate the
federal government is going to regulate
trade between different states in the
beginning it's going to be ineffective
but it's going to be an important
precedent the other big one you should
know about is the Sherman Antitrust Act
this is is going to Outlaw trust and
other monopolies that fix prices and
restrained trade and unfortunately for
labor unions it's going to be used
against them in the beginning not
against the monopolies that will change
however with the presidency of Theodore
Roosevelt during the Progressive
Movement in Period 7 another important
thing that's happening during this time
period is the movement of people and
we're talking about large scale internal
within the United States and external
migration is taking place place we
already saw the internal settlers
seeking opportunities on the frontier
out in the west you know and remember
these opportunities are available as a
result of the Homestead Act and the
completion of the Transcontinental
Railroad they are going west you're
going to see the mass movement of people
to urban areas as they're looking for
jobs and hoping to get economic
opportunities African-Americans are
going to really begin to move out of the
South slowly at first in the around the
1890s but it's going to increase
especially during World War I and World
War II leaving Jim Crow laws segregation
and heading to Northern cities this will
eventually be called The Great Migration
and you're going to have external
migration of people taking place large
scale immigration from China during this
period this will slow down dramatically
with the passage of the Chinese
Exclusion Act make sure you know about
that and after 1880 you're going to have
a different kind of immigrant coming in
from Europe the so-called new immigrants
from Southern and EAS Eastern Europe and
we're talking places like Russia Italy
Poland where my peeps are from and
others they are largely going to settle
in urban areas looking for job
opportunities that are presented as a
result of the Industrial Revolution
there is going to be a response to this
changing immigration and that is going
to be the rise of nativism in fact
during this time period there's going to
be various attempts to exclude and keep
out immigrants we've already heard about
the Chinese Exclusion Act effectively
shutting out Chinese immigration to the
United States the American Protective
Association was an anti-catholic group
made up of American Protestants that
wanted to get restrictions and limits on
the number of Catholics coming in and
you have various proposals for literacy
test which was proposed to keep Southern
and Eastern immigrants out of the US and
the idea here is that these immigrants
are undesirable they're going to
undermine and ruin the American way
there are going to be very challenges of
urbanization and immigration cities were
often divided among classes between the
rich and the poor races ethnicities
ethnic groups for example the Italians
in Little Italy the Chinese in San
Francisco are going to form their own
communities and cultures low wages and
dangerous working conditions kept many
workers in extreme poverty since you
have so many workers confined in these
cities unskilled work leads to low wages
there's going to be a contrast during
this time between the poor and the
wealthy and the wealthy are enjoying
lives of conspicuous consumption they're
able to spend huge amounts of money to
show off publicly their economic power
and Status that's not the reality for
the majority of people living in the
cities in fact many people in cities
like New York are going to be living in
tenement housing it was extremely common
and Jacob Reese is going to document
this in his famous piece how the other
half lives in
1890 giving a reality check to many
Americans child labor is becoming
increasingly common during this time and
immigrants attempted to both assimilate
for example learn English adopt to
mainstream American culture while also
maintaining their own unique cultural
identities and political machines
dominated City Life by exchanging
Welfare Services food and other things
and jobs for political support and this
creates all sorts of corruption and
fraud and waste however these challenges
are going to begin to be addressed
during the Gilded Age you have the
gospel of wealth which was a belief that
the wealthy had a moral obligation to
help out those less fortunate Andrew
Carnegie talked about this in his peace
wealth settlement house movement sought
to relieve Urban poverty and provide
assistance to immigrants um and you see
this with Jane Adams whole house in
Chicago Chicago helping immigrants
transition to life in America the social
gospel movement challenged the dominant
corporate ethic of the time and this was
a group of Christians which said
Christians had a responsibility to deal
with Urban poverty and to help alleviate
it the Socialist Party and other
organizations actually challenged
capitalism itself called it exploitive
and critiqued it you had Edward Bellamy
and his Looking Backward a utopian
socialist Society is depicted in this
novel and in this Society they have
fixed the social and economic injustices
of the time in fact the Socialist Party
is going to run candidates for political
offices at both the state and National
level and eventually and this is in
Period 7 the effort to reform these
problems will eventually lead to a
movement known as the Progressive
Movement in the 1890s and we got some
videos on that as well check them out
finally not only are there going to be
people addressing the economic problems
of the guilded age you're going to have
people addressing the social ones as
well the National American women
suffrage association NASA sought to
secure the right to vote for women the
right of suffrage you have people like
Elizabeth cat Stanton and Carrie Chapman
cat working tirelessly throughout this
time period trying to get the right to
vote various African American leaders
sought to advance the cause of civil
rights important one for period six is
Booker T was Washington and he advocated
African-Americans should acquire
vocational skills job skills to gain
self-respect and economic security he
established the Tuskegee Institute to
try to accomplish this goal and Idol
whales Barnett was very active in not
only the women's rights movement but
also in the campaign against lynching
that's a real quick rundown review this
is not meant to teach you everything in
aush Period 6 but it's a reminder if you
want some more details you you want all
the little details that's going to help
you get that five click on any one of
those four
videos if you haven't already done so
make sure you click that button and
subscribe tell all your friends to do
the same let them know how you're
getting all those A's in your a push
class if you have any questions post
them in the comments and if the video
helped you out click like have a great
day peace